Choosing a saddle can be not only a difficult decision, but one that requires a lot of time and patience in shopping.
It helps if we start out understanding what we're buying and what we might expect to pay.
I usually coach my clients in trying to find the very best used saddle possible.
If they are in fact in a bit of a budgeted plan.
If we buy a brand new saddle, one we have to break it in, and sometimes it's fun to have that happen before we get it.
But it's also going to be very pricey, and it may become even more pricey as we look at the time that we have to spend shopping.
We want to start out with thinking about a synthetic saddle, although not my very favorite, it does fall in the more budgeted category.
We'll talk about the merits of the synthetic versus leather down the road.
But these saddles can be found even brand new for as low as two hundred fifty to three hundred dollars.
As I move into my youth saddles, a brand new saddle of this type might be about three hundred and fifty dollars to four hundred dollars.
We move on up to a nice barrel saddle of a name brand, that's going to be better probably upwards of eight hundred dollars.
This saddle in its original show condition could bring it up to near a thousand.
As we move on forward, some of these more showy saddles as well as a really good functional cutting saddle, you can go with name brands that will take you as high as three thousand and upward, I've seen them as high as six thousand.
So you can see you've got a wide variety of choices, and you're going to have to decide within your budget what's your best option.